<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable George Earl of Berkeley, Governour, and the Company of Merchants of England trading into the Levant Seas at St. Peters Church in Broadstreet, January, 25, 1680 / by Charles Hickman ...</title>
            <author>Hickman, Charles, 1648-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 49 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A43698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1896</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11269</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11822506</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11822506</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A43698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 496:36)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Right Honourable George Earl of Berkeley, Governour, and the Company of Merchants of England trading into the Levant Seas at St. Peters Church in Broadstreet, January, 25, 1680 / by Charles Hickman ...</title>
                  <author>Hickman, Charles, 1648-1713.</author>
                  <author>Berkeley, George Berkeley, Earl of, 1628-1698.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Brome ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  John IV, 21-23.</term>
               <term>Samaritans --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Jews --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2008-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2008-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49603:1"/>
            <p>SERMON Preached before the RIGHT HONOURABLE <hi>GEORGE</hi> Earl of <hi>Berkeley,</hi> GOVERNOUR, AND THE Company of Merchants of ENGLAND Trading into the <hi>Levant</hi> Seas.</p>
            <p>AT St. PETERS Church in <hi>Broadſtreet. January</hi> 25. 1680.</p>
            <p>By <hi>CHARLES HICKMAN,</hi> A. M. Student of Chriſt-Church in <hi>Oxon,</hi> and Chaplain to his Excellency the Lord <hi>Chandois,</hi> Embaſſadour to <hi>Conſtantinople.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Brome</hi> at the Gun at the Weſt-End of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49603:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:49603:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable <hi>George</hi> Earl of <hi>Berkley,</hi> GOVERNOUR, And to the Right Worſhipful THE DEPUTY and COMPANY of Merchants trading into the <hi>Levant</hi> Seas.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable and Right Worſhipful,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F I had judged this Diſcourſe worthy of the Preſs, both the general conſent whereby you ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour'd me with the Title of your Servant, and the particular expreſsions of your Favour to me, would have obliged me to publiſh my gratitude in this Dedication, though you had not obliged me by your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. But ſince I underſtand how unreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably I am cenſured for this Diſcourſe, and that thoſe cenſures muſt in ſome manner re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect
<pb facs="tcp:49603:3"/>
upon you alſo, who have been pleaſed to afford me a more favourable Character; I find my ſelf bound in honour, as well as in gratitude and obedience, to vindicate both you, and my ſelf, by this Publication. The objections I need not here either repeat, or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; they are ſo groundleſs, that every ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional man will be ſatisfied by reading the Sermon, and they which are otherwiſe, will not be convinced by an Epiſtle. Againſt theſe I humbly beg your Protection, and as in duty bound, I ſhall ever pray for your happineſs, and Dedicate my ſelf wholly to your ſervice.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord, and Gentlemen,</salute>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your moſt obliged and Moſt humble ſervant</hi> Charles Hickman.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49603:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON ON
<q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOHN iv. 21, 12, 23.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Jeſus ſaith unto her, Woman believe me, the hour cometh when ye ſhall neither in this mountain, nor yet at Jeruſalem worſhip the Father.</p>
                  <p>Ye worſhip ye know not what, we know what we worſhip, for ſalvation is of the Jews.</p>
                  <p>But the hour cometh, and now is when the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit and in Truth.</p>
               </q>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N theſe words our Saviour deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mines the great Controverſie which had long depended be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Samaritans,</hi> as it was propoſed to him by the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> in theſe words. <hi>Our Fathers worſhipped in this mountain, but ye ſay that at Jeruſalem is the place where men ought to worſhip.</hi> Therefore for the full, and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49603:4"/>
underſtanding of my Text, I ſhall conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<list>
                  <item>1. The difference between the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. Our Saviours method of reconciling it, and</item>
                  <item>3. I ſhall apply the whole in ſome uſeful re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections upon the differences of theſe our times.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The difference between the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans</hi> was this; When the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were carried Captive into <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> the King of that Land tranſplanted ſeveral Inhabitants of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the Neighbouring Provinces there, and placed them in the Country of <hi>Samaria:</hi> where at the firſt they worſhipped their own Gods, without any reſpect to the God of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> But being terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by Lions which infeſted their Land, they wiſely imputed this their danger to ſome miſtake in their Religion, concluding that the God of the Land had brought this Calamity upon them for the neglect of his own worſhip, <hi>for they knew not the manner of the God of the Land.</hi> Upon com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint hereof their King ſent them one of the Prieſts of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to inſtruct them; the Prieſt built them an Altar and a Temple, and appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Sacrifices therein, and ſo made a formal ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of an Independent Church of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs though they feared the Lord, yet they ſerved their Graven Images alſo, for they thought they had ſufficiently appeaſed the God of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:49603:4"/>
the Land by appointing Sacrifices to him, but they could not forget the Gods of their Native Country; ſo they ſet up <hi>Adramelech and Anamelech, the Gods of Sepharvaim,</hi> every Nation according to their own inventions, and their Devotion was abſurdly divided betwixt the Idol and the living God.</p>
            <p>This was the riſe and original of the <hi>Samaritan</hi> Sect, in the days of <hi>Salmaneſer,</hi> ſeven hundred years before our Saviours time: this was the true Antiquity of their Church, as we find it Recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded 2 <hi>Kings</hi> xvii. Howbeit this was not the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity pleaded by the woman in my Text, neither were theſe the <hi>Fathers</hi> which ſhe affirmed to have <hi>worſhipped in the mountain,</hi> but as Nations, ſo Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions alſo love to boaſt of a long deſcent, and derive their pedegree, if it be poſſible, from the beginning of time: and if they want ſufficient Authority to make good their plea, a ſmall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence or Tradition will ſerve their turn, and ſuch a one it was whereby the <hi>Samaritans</hi> endeavoured to juſtifie their ſeparation.</p>
            <p>For the Authority of <hi>Salmaneſer</hi> not being ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to eſtabliſh a Church in oppoſition to the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they could find out no better expedient both to quiet their own Conſciences, and anſwer the objections of their Adverſaries the <hi>Jews,</hi> than by pleading a greater Antiquity for their Religion than the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves pretended
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49603:5"/>
to, and that the worſhipping upon that mountain was countenanced at leaſt, if not commanded, before the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was built, and this was no hard thing to prove. For we read <hi>Gen.</hi> xxviii. that <hi>Jacob</hi> travelling over this moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to <hi>Padan-Aram,</hi> ſaw a viſion of Angels aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending and deſcending; therefore <hi>he took the ſtone which he had put for his Pillow and put it up for a Pillar, poured Oil upon the top of it, and called the the name of that place</hi> Bethel, <hi>and he vowed a vow, that if God would be with him, and bring him back to his Fathers houſe in peace; then the Lord ſhould be his God, and that ſtone which be ſet up for a Pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſhould be Gods houſe, and he would ſurely pay his tenths.</hi> And <hi>Gen.</hi> xxxiii. at his return he did <hi>buy this parcel of ground and built an Altar there and called it El Elohe Iſrael. (i. e.)</hi> God the God of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> according as he promiſed. This is that <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thel</hi> which was afterwards made the Seat of the Prieſts of <hi>Samaria,</hi> and the ſolemn place of their worſhip, for ſo we read in the forecited chap. of 2 <hi>Kings, Then one of the Prieſts whom they had carried away from</hi> Samaria, <hi>came and dwelt in</hi> Bethel <hi>and taught them how they ſhould fear the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here we find a very plauſible pretence for the <hi>Samaritan</hi> ſervice, and ſince it was ſo contrary both to their eaſe and intereſt to go up to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to Sacrifice, no wonder if they made uſe of this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to ſerve God nearer home. And now the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49603:5"/>
womans boaſt ſounds big and ſignificant, <hi>Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers worſhipped in this mountain: Our Fathers</hi> ever ſince <hi>Jacobs</hi> time: <hi>Our Fathers</hi> for theſe eighteen hundred years, which was ſeven hundred years before the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was built: and yet <hi>Ye ſay that at</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>is the place where men ought to worſhip.</hi> That by <hi>their Fathers</hi> they reckon'd from their Father <hi>Jacob</hi> we may conclude. 1. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe <hi>Jacob,</hi> as we have heard did really worſhip in that Mountain. 2. Becauſe they call <hi>Jacob Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> with a particular expreſſion of Reverence; <hi>Art thou greater than our Father</hi> Jacob? 3. Becauſe an Argument drawn from their Fathers worſhip, had been of no force, if the date of that worſhip had not commenced before the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and the <hi>Samaritans</hi> muſt have confeſſed themſelves, as indeed they were, Schiſmaticks and Apoſtates from the Church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> they had then expoſed themſelves to that terrible objection from the <hi>Jews, Where was your Religion before</hi> Salmaneſer? Whereas now they could confidently ſay to the <hi>Jews</hi> themſelves, <hi>where was your Religion before</hi> So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon? when they thought their own as Ancient as their <hi>Father Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And no wonder that they ſhould call <hi>Jacob Father,</hi> and pretend to be of the ſeed of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> For though after the Captivity the Land was at firſt inhabited by the <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Nations, yet in proceſs of time many of the diſcontented <hi>Jews,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:49603:6"/>
conſulting their eaſe, their intereſt, or their humour, revolted to their worſhip, when they had once made an appearance of a Church. It was no new thing for the <hi>Jews</hi> to worſhip new Gods, and then much more might they worſhip him after a new faſhion. Novelties were ſtill delightful to this unſtable people, and they were always flexible to every evil way, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtifnecked when they ſhould return unto the truth.</p>
            <p>But if their calling <hi>Jacob Father</hi> be not a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient proof that they were of the ſame Original with the <hi>Jews,</hi> yet we may well judg they were <hi>Brethren,</hi> by the <hi>wrongs they did one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi> No enmity is ſo great as that between di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided friends; and as we obſerve in the Heavens, ſo likewiſe upon Earth, there is no direct oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but between thoſe Bodies which move in the ſame Line, and have ſometimes been in Conjunction: and this was the caſe of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Samaritans:</hi> there was ſuch a perfect abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt them, and the difference of their Religion (little as it was, in reſpect of other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) bred ſuch a diſtance and ſtrangeneſs in their Converſation, that though they ſlighted all the world beſides, yet they only hated one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother. The <hi>Jews</hi> accounted all Nations as <hi>ſtrangers</hi> to them, but the <hi>Samaritans</hi> as their <hi>ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> which ſhews that they looked not upon them
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49603:6"/>
as Proſelytes to their Church, but Apoſtates from their Communion. Therefore there was no Neighbourhood or Correſpondence amongſt them, which made the woman admire and ſay, <hi>How is that thou being a Jew askeſt water of me who am a woman of Samaria. For,</hi> ſays the Evangeliſt, <hi>The Jews have no dealing with the Samaritans.</hi> And therefore the <hi>Samaritans</hi> refuſed to entertain our Saviour, <hi>Becauſe his face was as though he would go to Jeruſalem.</hi> Thoſe common civilites which Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teaches us to ſhew unto all mankind, were here denied and grown out of date, becauſe they were almoſt, but not altogether of the ſame Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion
<q>
                  <l>—En quo diſcordia cives</l>
                  <l>Perduxit miſeros —</l>
               </q>
'Tis ſtrange that the worſhip of God, which was deſigned to unite the minds of men, and confirm the bonds of friendſhip, ſhould be taught to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide our hearts, and ſet Brother againſt Brother! That Religion, which is the higheſt improvement of Nature, ſhould blot out our firſt Principles of love, and make us forget our Natural Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons! However a <hi>Jew</hi> may juſtifie himſelf in this obſtinacy and hardneſs of heart, yet certainly we have otherwiſe learned Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:49603:7"/>2. Therefore I proceed to ſhew our Saviours method of reconciling this difference; And as a Preface thereunto we cannot chuſe but admire this wonderful inſtance of his Humility, how his Goodneſs here uſhered in his Truth, and by the tender expreſſions of his Love, he made way for the power of his Reaſons. Here we find the God of Truth converſing with a <hi>Samaritan</hi> that lived in an Idolatrous errour; the powers of Heaven and Earth, condeſcending to the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of a woman; and ſhe a Harlot too, living in Adultery, though he was the perfection of all Vertue and Goodneſs. Nevertheleſs foregoing all theſe inequalities, and forgetting the Native quarrel of their Countries, he friendly ſalutes her, as if he were not a <hi>Jew,</hi> or ſhe were no <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritan.</hi> He friendly informs her who he was, and confirms to her his Power, by diſcovering the ſecrets of her heart; at length being convinced that he was a Prophet, ſhe propoſes to him the grand queſtion in debate, <hi>Our fathers worſhipped in this mountain, and ye ſay that at Jeruſalem is the place where men ought to worſhip.</hi> To this, and to the whole controverſie between them, our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our makes anſwer in three diſtinct Heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. To the place of Worſhip.</item>
               <item>2. To the object of Worſhip.</item>
               <item>3. To the manner of Worſhip.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49603:7"/>And 1. to the place, the anſwer is: <hi>The hour cometh when ye ſhall neither in this mountain, nor yet at Jeruſalem worſhip the Father.</hi> That is, the time is coming, when the worſhip of God ſhall not neceſſarily be confined, either to the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> as it is at this day, or to the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of <hi>Samaria,</hi> as ye pretend, but all places ſhall be indifferent unto God, and it ſhall be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for all Nations to appoint unto themſelves ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn places of worſhip, without reſpect either to the Temple or the Mountain.</p>
            <p>For while the promiſe was made only to <hi>Iſrael</hi> and his Seed, there was a partition-wall between them and the Gentiles, and their Sacrifices, which were the types of that promiſe, were confined to their own Land: therefore their worſhip was <hi>particular,</hi> and their Religion <hi>local,</hi> being continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally celebrated in one place. Which place in former days, whilſt <hi>Iſrael</hi> was a Sojourning Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was changeable at pleaſure: and removed with their tents. Thus <hi>Jacob</hi> ſet up a Pillar and called it <hi>Bethel,</hi> the Houſe of God. And for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Ages the Ark removed from houſe to houſe: but when their Nation was ſettled in the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> and God had choſen <hi>Sion for his habitation, and his reſting place;</hi> then were all their Sacrifices conſigned to the Houſe of God, which was built at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> according as he had foretold, <hi>Deut.</hi> xii. 5. <hi>But unto the place which the Lord your God
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:49603:8"/>
ſhall chooſe out of all your Tribes, to put his name there, even to his habitation ſhall ye ſeek, and thither ſhall ye come, and thither ſhall ye bring your burnt Offerings, your Sacrifices, and your Tithes.</hi> Here we find a reſtraint put upon the liberty which the Nation formerly enjoyed, and though <hi>Jacob</hi> ſet up an Altar, and vowed to offer up his Tithes at <hi>Bethel,</hi> yet now they would only be accepted at the Temple in <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> and neither Prince nor people could ſeparate themſelves from the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of that place (as the <hi>Samaritans</hi> did) without the guilt of diſobedience and Schiſm.</p>
            <p>Nevertheleſs our Saviour lays not this crime to their charge, but tells them this diſpute is now growing out of date. The time is coming when the partition-wall ſhall be broken down, and all Nations ſhall be equally admitted to the worſhip of God, without any compliance to the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church, which being both temporary, and local, was now in the <hi>fulneſs of time</hi> to be utterly aboliſhed. though the promiſe was made only to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed; and that promiſe ſolemnized only at the Temple; yet the time was coming when the Temple ſhould be deſtroyed, and God would <hi>raiſe up from thoſe ſtones,</hi> even from the ruins of the Temple; <hi>children unto Abraham.</hi> The mighty Fabrick ſhould fall down, and in three days a more glorious than that ſhould be erected inſtead thereof. So much for the Place.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:49603:8"/>2. As for the Object of their worſhip, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer is; <hi>Ye worſhip ye know not what, we know what we worſhip, for ſalvation is of the Jews.</hi> Here the <hi>Samaritan</hi> Church ſtood in great need of a Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation: for though they feared the Lord, yet they ſerved their own Gods alſo, after the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Nations. And though by the frequent Converſion of <hi>Jews</hi> to their Church they had laid by the groſſer parts of their Idolatry, yet they kept their Idols, and graven Images in their houſes, and worſhiped according to our Saviours words, <hi>they knew not what.</hi> In this reſpect our Saviour ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judges the Cauſe to the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> ſide, alledging that though the Ceremonial part of their worſhip was now expiring, yet the ſubſtance thereof ſhould never change, God is the ſame for ever, and the object of their worſhip ſhall remain throughout all Ages. They are the only Church which truly acknowledges the only true God, and therefore <hi>Salvation is of the Jews</hi> and from them it ſhall be derived to all other Nations.</p>
            <p>But 3. Though the <hi>Jews</hi> did worſhip the true God, yet the manner of worſhip was imperfect and deficient even amongſt them: and the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfection thereof conſiſted herein; while their ſervice depended upon outward forms alone, and they were taught to offer up the fruits of their bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily labour for the Sins of their Soul; whilſt they meaſured their obedience by theſe dead works of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:49603:9"/>
the Law, and their devotion only by hearing or repeating the forms preſcribed by <hi>Moſes;</hi> then could this people draw nigh unto God with their mouths, when their heart was far from him. When the Sacrifice was ended, their work was done; and they could return to their ſins with this ſatisfaction, that the ſcape-Goat, in the wilderneſs had carryed off all their tranſgreſſions that were paſt, and the Goats in their Folds could expiate for all that was to come. Thus they thought they might obtain forgiveneſs of their ſins, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Reformation of their Minds: for their <hi>Fleſh</hi> was always willing, but their <hi>Spirit</hi> was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways weak.</p>
            <p>Thus the <hi>Jews</hi> worſhipped the true God by types and figures, but the <hi>Samaritans</hi> worſhiped types and figures for the true God: that worſhip was true but imperfect, this was neither perfect nor true. Therefore for the inſtruction of both <hi>Jew</hi> and <hi>Samaritan,</hi> our Saviour tells them that <hi>The hour cometh and now when the true worſhippers ſhall worſhip the Father in Spirit and in Truth. In Spirit</hi> firſt, to diſtinguiſh the Goſpel-ſervice from the ſhadows of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Law, which in Scripture are called <hi>carnal ordinances.</hi> And then in <hi>Truth</hi> to divide it from the <hi>Samaritan</hi> Idolatry, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſuperſtitious errors. To worſhip in <hi>Spirit</hi> therefore is to bow the knees of our heart, and not content our ſelves with the outward devotion
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49603:9"/>
of the body alone, <hi>which could not make him that did the ſervice perfect, as pertaining to the Conſcience;</hi> but to offer up the only acceptable Sacrifice of a <hi>bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and contrite Spirit.</hi> To worſhip God in <hi>Truth</hi> is to worſhip the true God in ſuch a manner as he has directed, without profaning his ſervice, as the <hi>Samaritans</hi> did, by a mixture of Heatheniſh Superſtitions, and Idols which are called <hi>lies.</hi> And thoſe who thus worſhip the Father <hi>in Spirit and in Truth,</hi> our Saviour terms the <hi>true worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers:</hi> for the diſcovery of whom I proceed in the third place to apply the former diſcourſe to the preſent times, that by our Saviours deciding this Controverſie, we may be able to paſs ſome judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the Controverſies of theſe our days, which have ſo miſerably rent our Nation, and do lively repreſent unto us the antient diſcord be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Jews</hi> and the <hi>Samaritans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And herein I muſt beg your favour and patience, if I am neceſſarily led, not by my own inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but by the method of my Text; to touch upon ſome of thoſe ſores which ſo unhappily af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict us, that they cannot be heal'd without hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, nor handled without regret and pain: and yet as I ſhall avoid all unneceſſary, unprofitable provocations, and endeavour with a tender hand not to enlarge, but to cloſe the wound; ſo I hope none will be offended at this charitable de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, eſpecially in defence of that Church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49603:10"/>
of we all here profeſs our ſelves to be Members.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Then, As in thoſe days, ſo now alſo we find, that of all the diſputes which divide the hearts of men, and diſaffect them from each other, there are none raiſed with more Ignorance and Pride, carried on with more Heat and Animoſity, nor concluded with more Labour and Difficulty, than thoſe which concern Religion, and the different ways of worſhipping God. No Opinion is ſo abſurd but it will ſerve to lay the foundation of a Schiſm amongſt the diſcontented inconſiderate multitude; and gain ſturdy Proſelytes too, in ſpight of all the convictions of Reaſon; if it can plead either eaſe or intereſt in its behalf. For though all Nations do agree in the certainty of a God, and the neceſſity of his worſhip, yet when men think themſelves ſo wonderfully wiſe, that neither the height nor depth of his wiſdom are beyond his reach; when they will intrude into the Counſels of the Almighty, and ſhape his wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip according to the extravagance of their fancy, then does their wiſdom degenerate into igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and the ſtrength of their reaſon only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trays them to labour and folly. <hi>Hardly do we gueſs aright at the things upon Earth, and with labour do we find the things that are before us; but the things that are in Heaven who hath ſearched out, and thy Counſels who hath known?</hi> ſaid the wiſeſt of men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49603:10"/>But though the Ignorance of man be great, yet generally his Pride is greater than that; and thoſe falſe Notions which in his vanity he has concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, in his obſtinacy he will defend. There are few ſo ingenuous as to confeſs an error, and the moſt ignorant are always the hardeſt to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince. They will impoſe their own fancies upon others with that eagerneſs, as if they really were, what they falſly ſtile them, the only Divine Truths, and immediate Revelations of God; and to disbelieve their Opinion, is to renounce their friendſhip. Thus the Heathens, though they had no knowledg of God, yet they alſo would fight <hi>pro aris &amp; focis,</hi> for their Gods, as well as their Country; and the ſharpeſt Perſecutions that the world ever ſaw, were raiſed by the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Emperors firſt, and after them by their Succeſſors, the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Biſhops, againſt the profeſſours of the true Primitive Chriſtianity. No wars are ſo bloody as thoſe which are backed with Religion; and when men fight, juſt as they pray, for <hi>they know not what,</hi> the contention grows warm ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Zeal of the Combatants, and the war will end <hi>they know not when.</hi> For Empire may more eaſily be confined, like the Ocean within its banks; and Intereſt knows its own bounds; only Opinion is a boundleſs thing; like the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing of a River, it ſpreads itſelf far and wide; and our thoughts, which are ungovernable in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49603:11"/>
themſelves, cannot be overruled by any power. No preſcription can be pleaded in the things of God, and no length of time can reconcile the difference of belief. The Sword it ſelf which decides all other Controverſies, has no control over the Minds and Conſciences of men, and though the <hi>Iron enters into their very ſouls,</hi> yet it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſubdue, or change one thought therein.</p>
            <p>What ſhall we ſay then? is it the happineſs or misfortune of our Natures, that our Spirits are thus invincible, and no Authority is ſo great as that which governs in our own breaſt? 'Tis a happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in this, that <hi>neither tribulation nor anguiſh, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution nor death, principalities nor powers, can ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate us from the love of Chriſt,</hi> and the Faith in his Name; but 'tis a misfortune likewiſe, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>height nor depth, nor Angels nor Men, nor things preſent nor things to come,</hi> can reclaim us from a falſe Religion, or bring us into the paths of peace. 'Tis a happineſs to thoſe that have embraced the Truth, but a curſe to them that live in Error. And ſince every Party and Faction, how erroneous ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, does yet conclude it ſelf to be in the right, from hence we may learn that the True Religion <hi>muſt not,</hi> becauſe it <hi>cannot,</hi> be propagated by vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence and blood; but amidſt all the ſeveral pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, whereby ſo many, and ſo different Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties lay claim to the only true Church, if we would know to whom this infant Primitive
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:49603:11"/>
Truth belongs, we muſt direct our judgment as the wiſe <hi>Solomon</hi> did, and give up the Cauſe to them that firſt lay down the Sword; Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Peace can never be divided; and the Goſpel of Truth is alſo the Goſpel of Love.</p>
            <p>With what pretence then of Piety, or Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, can the enemies of our Faith juſtifie their reproachful and deſpightful uſage of us? That they ſhould endeavour thus by Fire and Sword, to extirpate our Lives together with our Religion, and lay both our Church and Nation in the duſt. That they who are our Brethren, bone of our bone, and fleſh of our fleſh, ſhould riſe up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, and forget their Bowels of compaſſion, and their Fathers houſe. That they ſhould deny us the ordinary Civilities of mankind, and like <hi>Jews</hi> unto the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> allow no dealings with us. That they ſhould Excommunicate us from their Society with the out-caſt of the people, and brand a whole Church with the hateful title of wicked, and prophane. That they ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe to admit us to their houſes, becauſe we come not into their Temples; and reject us <hi>becauſe our faces are as though we would go to</hi> Jeruſalem. Have they found ſuch dealings from us? Has not our Church been ſtill inviting them to her Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ready to embrace her greateſt adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries with the Arms of kindneſs? Is not Peace and Submiſſion her Glory, and Charity the very
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:49603:12"/>
Character whereby ſhe ſtands diſtinguiſhed from all other Churches? Has it not been her conſtant Practice, as well as Profeſſion, to promote a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation of all differences where it may be had, and only lament the want of it where it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be obtained; to be induſtrious for the union and conſent of her Children, and favourably charitable to all peaceful Diſſenters? Nay is ſhe not upbraided for being ſo? Is not this her Charity and Kindneſs become her reproach, and an occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to her adverſaries to ſlander her for Heretical on the one hand, and Popiſh on the other? And as ſuch ſhe has been uſed, ſhe has ſuffered Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrdom under both theſe ſhapes, and as the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> dealt with the Primitive Chriſtians; ſo they alſo put us under the hateful diſguiſes of Lions, and Bears, and then worry us, as if we were ſuch indeed.</p>
            <p>But certainly we are not more Idolatrous, or more Heretical than the <hi>Samaritans;</hi> nor are they more Righteous than our Saviour. And yet he dealt not ſo with thoſe that were enemies both to him and the Truth. When his Diſciples would have called down fire from Heaven to puniſh their unkindneſs, he reproved their unwarranted Zeal, ſaying <hi>Ye Know not what Spirit ye are of,</hi> though their worſhip was Idolatrous, yet he would give even Idolaters their due, and allow them human affections, as well as human frailties: proving
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:49603:12"/>
that a <hi>Samaritan</hi> may be a good Neighbour, when neither Prieſt nor Levite would give two pence to deſerve that name. Though he was the wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of God from the beginning, yet he conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended to the weakneſs of a woman, which was an enemy both to his Church and Nation: he gently reproves her vice, and friendly corrects her errors, and though his Diſciples marveled at the ſight, yet he thought it no diſparagement to his Divinity; for he came to call ſinners to Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and Preach the Goſpel to the Poor. And no wonder that he ſhould do ſo, for what man is not both poor and ſinful in the ſight of God? How blind is the Knowledg, and how weak the Vertue of the beſt of us, when compared with thoſe infinite unmeaſurable powers which are in the Fountain and Foundation of all our good? And then how ſmall will the diſtance appear be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us men? 'Tis like the dividing of a tittle, the whole is ſo ſmall, that nothing but a Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying-Glaſs can diſcover the difference of the parts. One Star differeth from another Star in Glory, and though the Moon makes ſome diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very thereof, obſcuring one, and leaving an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect luſtre upon the other, yet the Sun Eclipſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all alike, all their glories diſappear before him, and ſo the great contention ceaſeth. Even ſo are our good deeds before God; they are ſo few, and ſo imperfect, that it is not our merit;
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49603:13"/>
but his mercy alone that creates the difference: he can forgive much as well as little; the <hi>Samaritan</hi> by him may be termed <hi>good,</hi> and the Publican admitted to his preſence, when the obſtinate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited Phariſee ſhall be for ever excluded.</p>
            <p>Therefore why boaſteſt thou thy ſelf, O vain man, as if all the treaſures of vertue and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg were centered in thy own breaſt? Who is ignorant and thou art not ignorant, who is ſinful and thou art not ſo? Deſpiſe not then the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thy Brother, leſt thou alſo be deſpiſed; judg not his infirmities, leſt thereby thou bring a juſt judgment upon thy own head, leſt thou alſo be ſeverely judged by the Righteous God; But rather ſtudy peace with all men, be juſt to their merits, favourable to their frailties, and only ſevere upon thy own ſelf. So will God accept of thy humility, and thy humility will recommend thy Faith; as thou haſt dealt with others, ſo will God deal with thee alſo he will reward thy good deeds, and pardon what thou in ignorance haſt done amiſs. Then ſhall thy worſhip be always acceptable in his ſight, and by granting thy hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petitions, he will turn all thy Prayers into Praiſes and Thankſgiving.</p>
            <p>This is the firſt Character of the true worſhip taken from the temper of the worſhippers, 'tis our Saviours own Rule, <hi>Ye ſhall know them by their fruits,</hi> and the Fruits of the Goſpel we know,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49603:13"/>
are Peace, Charity, Humility and Love; <hi>Love is the fulfilling of the Law,</hi> and the great glory of the Goſpel, and where this virtue is wanting there can be no pretence of Godlineſs, no ſhew of a Chriſtian Church.</p>
            <p>The next Character may be taken from the place of worſhip; <hi>our fathers worſhiped in this moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> ſaid the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> to juſtifie their Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and ſo ſay the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> unto us, Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers worſhiped in this City, the Fathers of the Church plead for us, and Antiquity is on our ſide, and where was your Church before <hi>Luther?</hi> To this the Anſwer is as obvious as true, <hi>Our Fathers worſhiped at Rome,</hi> but not all our Fathers; for from the beginning there were ſeveral pious and learned Fathers and Martyrs of the Chriſtian faith, that own'd no dependence upon the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> There was then a <hi>Roman,</hi> but not a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Church. It was not Chriſtian Humility and the Primitive Simplicity of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, but Pride and Secular Intereſt that mov'd the later Paſtors of that Church to bring all Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions under their yoke. 'Twas that Lordly hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour which our Saviour reprov'd in the ſons of <hi>Zebedee,</hi> when they ſtrove to be accounted great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, telling them that this ambition more became the Heathens than his Diſciples; <hi>the Kings of the Gentiles, ye know, exerciſe dominion, but it ſhall not be ſo amongſt you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49603:14"/>
               <hi>Our fathers worſhipped at</hi> Rome, it may be ſo. So did <hi>Jacob</hi> in the mountain of <hi>Samaria,</hi> when the whole Church of God conſiſted only in him, and his Fathers houſe: and yet this was no plea againſt the worſhip of the Temple, when God had choſen that place for his Habitation; and our Fathers who themſelves worſhiped at <hi>Rome,</hi> have not told us that at <hi>Rome</hi> is the place where we alſo ought to worſhip. If there muſt ſtill be one <hi>Holy City to which all the tribes muſt go up,</hi> certainly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that City of Peace, had been a fitter place for the Seat of that Univerſal Empire, than <hi>Rome,</hi> which was always the Seat of War, and only made great by Tyrannies and Invaſions upon all the world. If that time of liberty be come when our worſhip ſhall not be confined either to the Temple of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> or the Mountain of <hi>Samaria,</hi> we may alſo conclude; that <hi>neither at</hi> Rome <hi>ſhall we worſhip the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But yet <hi>our Fathers worſhipped at</hi> Rome. 'Tis true, but <hi>Rome</hi> was not then what now it is; their Church and Faith was then as glorious as now tis offenſive to all the world. It exerciſed then no unjuſt Uſurpations, either upon the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons or Conſciences of men, but taught Obedience to God and his Vicegerents upon Earth. No man under what title ſoever ſat in the Seat of God, impoſing upon the belief of others, and creating new Articles of Faith; but in all things they ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49603:14"/>
themſelves to the word of God, as their only Univerſal Infallible Judg. And there was our Church before <hi>Luther,</hi> and even before Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry it ſelf. But now ſince her innovoations are mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed, and ſhe has departed from the Truth, no wonder if we forſake her in thoſe things wherein ſhe has forſaken Chriſt, and fly from this City, becauſe of her abominations. Her Fathers which worſhipped in that place, will not now juſtifie theſe degenerated Children, and ſince they boaſt ſo much of their antiquity, we muſt needs reckon the date of their worſhip, like that of the <hi>Samaritans,</hi> not from their <hi>Father Jacob,</hi> a Holy Patriarch, but from <hi>Salmaneſer,</hi> a <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Prince.</p>
            <p>Again, <hi>Our Fathers worſhipped in this mountain,</hi> and therefore ſo do we, ſaid the <hi>Samaritans.</hi> Thus alſo many amongſt us ſay. Our Fathers the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and Primitive Martys of the Church, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped in Mountains, Dens, Caves, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Houſes, and therefore ſo may we alſo. To this I anſwer that the Apoſtles worſhipped in the Temple and Publick Aſſemblies alſo, when they might be permitted; and it was only the ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity and neceſſity of the times that drove them into private places; which neceſſity being now removed, a ſeparation from the Publick Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies upon the bare account of Chriſtian Liberty, grounded upon that Practice of the Apoſtles, is
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49603:15"/>
no move juſtifiable, than that of the <hi>Samaritans</hi> from the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church upon the Authority of their Father <hi>Jacob.</hi> 'Tis as if we ſhould ſay, Our Fathers the Apoſtles admitted none into the Church by Baptiſm, unleſs they could firſt give an account of their Faith, and therefore now alſo it is unlawful to Baptiſe Infants that have no knowledg of Chriſt. Or thus, our Fathers <hi>Abel, Enoch,</hi> and others, were forced to marry their own Siſters, when there were no other women in the world, and therefore we may do the like. Here we ſee what was commendable in the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles is pernicious in us, what was neceſſary in our fore-Fathers is abominable Inceſt in our times: ſo deceitful may an Argument prove drawn from the practice of our Fathers, if we make not allowance for the different circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and neceſſities of the times.</p>
            <p>The third Character of the true worſhippers may be taken from the object of their worſhip. <hi>Ye worſhip ye know not what,</hi> ſaid our Saviour. And ſo may we alſo ſay to the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> ye worſhip Idols, Graven Images, Reliques, Sepulchres, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous Trifles, Superſtitious Legends, <hi>and ye know not what.</hi> And though perhaps the more wiſe and learned of that Communion may be ſo clear-ſighted, as to look beyond this veil of wood and ſtone, and have an Eye upon the true God, whom they thus falſly repreſent; yet certainly the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49603:15"/>
ignorant multitude fall down and pay a real wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to theſe beggarly Elements: and then how can they themſelves be excuſed, who by theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warranted practices have brought the people into Idolatry?</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt remark upon the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers of theſe times, may be concerning the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of their worſhip, which our Saviour has commanded to be <hi>in Spirit and in Truth.</hi> By <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> here we muſt underſtand, firſt, the faculties of the Soul, which is the <hi>Spirit of a man;</hi> and ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the gifts of the Holy Ghoſt, which is the <hi>Spirit of God.</hi> In the firſt ſence we are taught that <hi>God is a Spirit, and we muſt worſhip him in our Spirit;</hi> all our thoughts and inward faculties muſt be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed in his ſervice, and we muſt adore him with <hi>all our heart, our mind, our ſoul, and our ſtrength:</hi> our underſtandings muſt be clear and apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive of what we want; our Wills muſt be ready and active to draw up our wants into Petitions; and our affections muſt be zealous and inflamed to hand up our Petitions to the Throne of Grace: ſo ſpiritual and refined, that they may convey our Prayers to Heaven; ſo powerful and ſtrong as to bring down Heaven to us. And this is not to be done by painful noiſe and exerciſe of the Body, but by the quick and ſprightly motions of the ſoul. Theſe are the faculties which we muſt employ in the ſervice of God, and <hi>thus we muſt worſhip in Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49603:16"/>But what man is ſufficient for theſe things? Our underſtandings are naturally ſo dull, our wills ſo corrupt, and our affections ſo diſturbed, that of our ſelves we know not what to ask, nor how to Pray. Therefore when according to the firſt Rule we have by humility prepared our hearts for Prayer, then does the ſpirit of God deſcend upon us, and help our infirmities: he builds upon the Foundations of Nature, improves our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding into a ſtedfaſt Faith, quickens our wills and deſires with a ſure hope and confidence in God, and inflames our affections with a Divine love. He ſo enlightens our Eyes as that we may look up and behold the Heavens opened to admit our ſupplications, and ſo purifies our hearts that we may be worthy to receive the rays of Divine Majeſty into our boſom in the happy return of our Prayers. Theſe are the gifts or the Spirit whereby he directs and aſſiſts us in our Prayers and Suppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, and <hi>thus we muſt worſhip in Spirit and in Truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if we take our meaſures of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice by this Rule, we ſhall find it very deficient. As for inſtance, their Praying in an unknown Tongue. How can the ſpirit of a man be moved by that which he does not underſtand? How can a man be edified by thoſe words which only enter into his outward Ears, and never ſink into his heart? it is not the turning over ſo many Beads, nor the
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:49603:16"/>
kneeling ſo long upon our knees that compleats the worſhip of God, or prepares a Sacrifice wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of him; but the lifting up of our hearts, as well as our hands to his Holy place: therefore we may ſay of this ſort of Prayer as St. <hi>Paul</hi> did of the Preaching in his time, <hi>yet in the Church I had rather ſpeak five words with my underſtanding, that by my voice I might teach others alſo, than ten thouſand words in an unknown Tongue.</hi> This practice ſavours too much of the blind formal Devotion of a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Synagogue, and can never be proved to be the true Chriſtian worſhip, except they can convince us that miraculous effuſion of the Spirit is ſtill continued to the Church, and men may now un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand theſe unknown Tongues by the ſame Miracle whereby the Apoſtles ſpake them.</p>
            <p>And as the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church is deficient herein, ſo our Diſſenting Brethren, notwithſtanding all their pretences to the Spirit, do not at all abound; who by a new and ſtrange Interpretation have forced this expreſſion of <hi>worſhipping in the Spirit</hi> to ſignifie only <hi>Extempore Prayer,</hi> and confined all theſe No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Divine influences or the Holy Ghoſt, to the mean ungenerous purpoſes of ſupplying the defects of our ſpeech, and inventing words for our imperfect thoughts. As if forwardneſs of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, confidence of Face, and readineſs of the Tongue, which are the reproachful Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of a troubleſome Companion, were
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49603:17"/>
now become the only teſts of a gifted Brother.</p>
            <p>But ſuppoſing readineſs of Expreſſion to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally a gift of the Spirit, yet how ſhall we know by what Spirit it is that this man ſpeaks? There is a deluding Spirit, which under a pretence of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Piety has drawn multitudes together into extraordinary evils; and this is no new thing eſpecially in theſe our days. There is a Spirit of Contention, whereby many pretend to a more eminent degree of vertue, and yet intend only a more eminent place of honour to themſelves. Such was the Spirit whereby the Sons of <hi>Zebedee</hi> prayed, that they might ſit one on the right hand of our Saviour, and the other on the left. There is a Spirit of Vanity and Oſtentation, and ſuch a one it was that exalted <hi>Herod</hi> into his Throne, clothed him with his Royal Apparel, and prom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted to him that vain-glorious Oration which he made unto the people. All theſe Spirits fail not to give utterance to the perſon poſſeſſed therewith, according to the mighty working of their Error, their Intereſt, or their Pride: as particularly to <hi>Herod</hi> in ſo fluent and divine a manner, that the poor deluded people took him not for a man but God. Therefore it availeth very little for a man to have the gift of <hi>ſpeaking by the Spirit,</hi> except the people have the gift alſo of <hi>diſcerning the Spirit</hi> by which he ſpeaks; and this is a gift not very uſual or remarkable in thoſe that are the admirers of this ſort of worſhip.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49603:17"/>Since thercfore the Age of Miracles is gone, and the immediate impulſe of the Holy Ghoſt is departed from us, 'tis ſafer for us to truſt to thoſe Prayers which the wiſeſt and beſt of men amongſt us (even thoſe to whom under Chriſt we owe our Religion and Reformation) have compiled with great Piety and Prudence, and maintained with Conſtancy and Perſeverance, even to Martyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom; rather than to rely on the unskilful undi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted Prayers of every forward inconſiderate worſhipper. Who would not quit the wild ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving fancies of ſuch as Pray for they think not, <hi>they know not what;</hi> to joyn in theſe Petitions which are ſo plain and eaſie, that they are agreed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the capacities of the meaneſt; ſo judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and accurate as to ſatisfie the wiſeſt men: ſo full and copious as to ſupply the wants of the greateſt ſinners, ſo Subſtantial, Pious and Grave, as may befit the greateſt Saints?</p>
            <p>As for thoſe therefore, that quarrel with the <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> of our Prayers, we ſay no more but that all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man things are ſubject to errors, and when they can find out better we ſhall willingly ſubmit to the change. As for thoſe that find fault with the <hi>manner</hi> of them, and ſay theſe ſet Forms do ſtint the Holy Ghoſt, and <hi>quench the Spirit;</hi> I anſwer 'tis very ſtrange, that theſe words which were compoſed with the greateſt Art and Induſtry of man, and with as great a meaſure at leaſt of the Holy Spirit
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49603:18"/>
as any private perſon can pretend unto, ſhould come at length to be deſpiſed, as flat and inſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficant. Rhetorick and a well framed Compoſure were wont to raiſe our affections, and heighten our Devotion, and can nothing move us now but what is remarkable for being mean, and the rude product of our firſt thoughts? Certainly it is not the goodneſs, but the newneſs of this faſhion that draws the people after it; and the love of Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty is in all caſes a ſign of Levity, but in Religion it is commonly the cauſe of Superſtition. 'Tis on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a debauched and wanton ſtomach that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires variety of taſts, and a conſtant Appetite is not only the ſign, but alſo the cauſe of Health.</p>
            <p>But I would willingly know wherein a ſet form of Prayers does ſtint the Spirit; cannot our Spirit be touched with a ſence of our wants, and an ardent deſire of a ſupply as well by a <hi>premeditated</hi> as an <hi>extempore</hi> Prayer? Cannot we Pray as Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, and as effectually in that perfect form of words which were preſcribed by our Saviour, as in thoſe which are conceived by man? Cannot we lift up our hearts to God with as much Zeal and Devotion in one of the Pſalms of <hi>David</hi> (for they are <hi>Spiritual Songs</hi>) as in the ſudden tranſports of a private Spirit? dares any man be ſo preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous, ſo blaſphemous, as to ſay that theſe Forms of worſhip are cold, jejune, and do ſtint the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit? where then is their Argument againſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Liturgies?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:49603:18"/>But what if the Spirit ſhould be ſtinted! A Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is an unruly thing, and 'tis fit it ſhould be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſcribed. If the Spirit of St. <hi>Peter</hi> had been confined within the bounds of Prudence, he had eſcaped many ſevere cenſures to which the evtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagance of his Zeal expoſed him. When he Prayed that they might build Altars to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias,</hi> the Evangeliſts upbraids him with a Spirit of inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration. When he Prayed againſt the Paſſion of our Saviour, he rebuked his Spirit for Diabolical; ſaying, <hi>Get thee behind me Satan.</hi> And if the Spirit of the Great Apoſtle was ſubject to ſuch er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors in Prayer, what greater confidence can we have in our new unpractiſed uninſpired profeſſors?</p>
            <p>To conclude, if neither the command of our Saviour, nor the practice of all ſettled Churches throughout the world, both Jewiſh and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, can be of ſufficient Authority to weigh down this new Model of Divinity: if nothing but Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematical Demonſtrations can convince them of the truth, and the leaſt ſhadow of an Argumcnt will ſerve to confirm them in their errors: if nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſon nor kindneſs can reclaim them: I hope 'tis no breach of Charity to think that it is not the <hi>Spirit of Prayer,</hi> but the <hi>Spirit of Oſtentation</hi> that animates their Aſſemblies, and encourages this ungrounded Separation. And ſince all hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man means have proved ineffectual, we muſt commit the Cauſe to God, who is the ſearcher
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49603:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of all hearts, and Pray that by the power of his love he would come amongſt us, and turn the hearts of out diſaffected Brethren: That he would remove their prejudices, and enlighten their underſtandings; abate their heats, and warm their affections towards us, that they would leave off their uncharitable cenſures, and ſhew forth the purity of their Faith by their <hi>certain</hi> gifts of the Spirits, Humility and Love. That they would for once ſuppoſe us to be but as Wiſe, as Vertuous, and as Sincere as they; and after a kind impartial tryal, I doubt not but their Charity will either pronounce us <hi>good,</hi> or their Converſation will make us better.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
